Sometimes when making a game you'll need
ゲームを作成するときに
a smooth transition between two values.
ふたつの値の間をスムーズに遷移させることが必要な場合があります。
A common example is smoothing a change
良くある例は位置の変動をスムーズに
in position. You can do this using a
行なうことです。このことは
function called Lerp. Lerp is short for
Lerp と呼ばれる関数を使用して行なうことが出来ます。Lerp とは
Linear Interpolation. In this scene we have
Linear Interpolation （線形補間）の略です。このシーンでは
a light and script that lerps three
ライトおよびすうりぷとがあり、
properties of the light. It's position,
ライトのプロパティを 3 つ補間します。Position、
colour and intensity.
Color および Intensity です。
Let's take a look at how we use lerp for
それでは Lerp を使用して各々のプロパティを
each of these properties.
使用する方法を見ていきます。
First off, position. In this unfinished
初めに、Position です。この未完成のサンプルでは
example I have a variable to store
新しい Vector3 の位置を
a new vector3 position
格納する変数があり、
holding X, Y and Z
X, Y, Z があります。
In Awake I set this value to the current
Awake の中で、この値を
position of the object by using
オブジェクトの現在の位置にセットするのに
transform.position.
transform.position を使用します。
Then in update we're running a position changing
次に Update の中で位置変更の関数を
function every frame.
毎フレーム実行します。
So what happens here? Well we have
では何が起きているのでしょう？
two more vector3 variables position A
さらに二つの Vector3 変数 位置 A および
and position B. These are two positions
位置 B があります。これらの二つの位置で
that I want to switch the light between.
ライトの位置を切り替えることにします。
Then I simply check for input when I
Q キーを押下したとき、
press the key Q,
入力をチェックします。
I move to position A. And when I press
次に位置 A に移動します。そして
the key E I move to position B.
E キーを押下したとき、位置 B に移動します。
And you can see here I'm setting the current
そして現在の位置を
position to this variable and constantly
この変数にセットして
changing between it. So let's see how that works.
継続的に変更を行なっています。それではどのように働くかみてみましょう。
If I press Q I move here, -5 in X.
もし Q キーを押下すると、X が -5 の位置に移動します。
And when I press E I get positive 5.
そして E を押下すると、+5 の位置に移動します。
But, as you can see, we're just jumping
みて分かるように
between those two positions, which is not
これらの二つの位置を行き来しているだけで
what we want. So this is where we use a Lerp
それはやりたいことではありません。ここで Lerp を使用して
to smoothly interpolate between
二つの値の間をスムーズに補間
those two values.
しておきます。
So instead of setting transform position
このため Transform の Position を
to the value of new position
新しい Position の値をセットする代わりに
we're going to say vector3.lerp.
Vector3.Lerp とします。
And the basic properties of a lerp are
そして Lerp の基本的なプロパティは
threefold. The 'from' value, the 'to' value
3 要素あります。 from の値、 to の値、
and a 'time' value.
そして time の値です。
So the starting value of this, because
このため開始時の値は、
it's the position will be the current
現在の位置であるため、
transform.position. That's the 'from' value.
transform.position とします。これが from の値に相当します。
Then we'll set the 'to' value
次に to の値に
with the variable newPosition.
newPosition 変数をセットします
And finally we need a value for 'time'.
そして最後に time の値が必要です。
So we'll use Time.deltaTime.
ここで Time.deltaTime を使用します。
Let's see how this looks.
どのようになるか見ていきます。
Now you can see we're smoothly interpolating
二つの位置の間をスムーズに補間していることが
between those two points.
みて分かります。
We might want to increase the speed at
これが発生しているスピードを
which this occurs, so we could add in
増やした場合は、
a variable to help us do this.
変数を追加して作業しやすくします。
I am going to add in a public float
ここでは public で float 型の変数を追加して
and I am going to call it smooth and
smooth と名前をつけて
I will start off with a value of 2.
最初の値を 2 にします。
Then I will simply multiply my delta time
次にその値と
by that value.
deltaTime と掛け算をします。
And now you can see our interpolation
二つの位置の間の補完が
between those two points is a lot quicker.
ずいぶん速くなったことが確認できます。
And because it's a public variable we
そして public 変数であるため、
can crank up the speed and do it
スピードを大きくあげて
nice and fast too.
さらに速くすることが出来ます。
Now let's look at changing the intensity.
それではライト強度（Intensity）の変更を見ていきます。
This once is slightly different because
これはわずかに異なるのですが、
we're using Mathf.Lerp rather than using
それは Mathf.Lerp を
vector3.Lerp. Mathf.Lerp will go between
Vector3.Lerp の代わりに使用するためです。Mathf.Lerp は
two float values rather than going between
二つの Vector3 の値を行き来する代わりに
two vector3 values.
二つの float の値の間を行き来します。
So if you have something that's using a
このためもし float を使用している何かがあれば
float you would used Mathf.Lerp, and something
Mathf.Lerp を使用するべきで、そして
that is using a vector3 you'd use
Vector3 を使用している何かがあれば
vector3.Lerp. This time around we've setup
Vector3.lerp を使用すべきです。今回のコードでは
our code for changing the intensity
ライト強度（Intensity）を変更する
of the light. We have a new intensity
ように準備しました。新しい Intensity の変数があります。
variable. We set it equal to the light
これを ゲーム開始時の
intensity at the start of the game
ライト強度と等しくなるようにして
and we're running intensity changing every frame.
そして毎フレームごとに Intensity の変更を実行します。
This time we have two different intensities
今回は二つの異なる Intensity があり
0.5 and positive 5.
0.5 と 5 です。
And then we're using the keys A and D
そしてA キーおよび D キーを使用して、
to set between these two intensity values.
この二つの Intensity の値で切り替えさせます。
So you can see that we're simply addressing
みれば分かるように、
the light component, it's intensity property
Light コンポーネント、Intensity プロパティをみつけて、
and setting it equal to a Mathf.Lerp.
その値を Mathf.Lerp と等しくしています。
The 'from' value is the current intensity
from の値は現在の Intensity であり、
and the value to interpolate towards
補間する終点側の値は
is the value of the new intensity variable.
新しい Intensity 変数の値です。
And yet again we are using Time.deltaTime
そして、ここでも Time.deltaTime を使用して
multiplied by our smoothing variable.
スムージングするための変数に掛け算します。
Let's see how this looks.
それではどのようになるか見てみましょう。
And as usual if our smoothing value differs
いつもと同様に、もしスムージングする値が異なる場合
we can increase the speed at which this
この補間が発生するスピードを
interpolation occurs.
増加させることが出来ます。1
Finally let's look at interpolating the colour.
最後に色の補間についてみていきます。
This time around we have setup a new colour
今回は上の方で新しい color 変数を
variable at the top. We have set it equal to
セットアップしました。それをゲーム開始時に
the light component's colour value when
Light コンポーネントの color の値に等しくなるようにしています。
the game starts. And yet again we have
そしてまた、
a function that is running every frame.
毎フレーム実行される関数があります。
We have two colour shortcuts
二つの色である
Colour.red and Colour.green
Color.red および Color.green を
stored in A and B variables
A および B 変数に格納して
and we're switching them with Z and C
そしてそれらを Z キーおよび C キーで
on the keyboard. As with our other lerps
切り替えます。他の Lerp と同様に
we have a 'from' and a 'to' value,
from および to の値があります。
the original light.colour and the new colour.
これはもとの Light.Color および新しい Color です。
And again we're using Time.deltaTime
今回も Time.deltaTime に
multiplied by smooth.
スムージング係数 smooth を掛け算しています。
Simple. So when I press play
ここまで簡単でした。 Play ボタンを押下すると
I can move between those values.
これらの値の間を移動させることが出来ます。
And if I want to increase the speed
そしてもしスピードを増加させたかった場合
I crank up my smooth value.
smooth の値を大きくします。
Let's take a look at the finished scene
これら全てが含まれる、完成したシーンを
with all of those included.
みてみましょう。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)